{"author": "Robert R. Harr","data": [{"chapter": "1.6","questions": [{"data": [{"choices": ["Acute myelomonocytic leukemia (M4)","Acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)","Acute myeloid leukemia without maturation (AML:M1)","Acute promyelocytic leukemia (PML; M3)"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)","explanation": "Auer rods are not seen characteristically in lymphoblasts. They may be seen in myeloblasts, promyelocytes, and monoblasts"},"question": "Auer rods may be seen in all of the following except:","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Acute leukemia/1"},{"choices": ["Microcytic, hyperchromic","Microcytic, hypochromic","Normocytic, normochromic","Macrocytic, normochromic"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Normocytic, normochromic","explanation": "Acute leukemia is usually associated with a normocytic normochromic anemia. Anemia in acute leukemia is usually present from the onset and may be severe; however, there is no inherent nutritional deficiency leading to a microcytic, hypochromic, or megaloblastic process"},"question": "Which type of anemia is usually present in a patient with acute leukemia?","reference": "Hematology/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/RBC microscopic morphology/Anemia/2"},{"choices": ["Myelophthisis","Dysplasia","Leukoerythroblastosis","Megaloblastosis"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Leukoerythroblastosis","explanation": "The presence of immature leukocytes and NRBCs is called leukoerythroblastosis and frequently denotes a malignant or myeloproliferative process. Myelophthisis refers to replacement of bone marrow by a disease process, such as a neoplasm. The development of abnormal tissue is called dysplasia"},"question": "In leukemia, which term describes the peripheral blood finding of leukocytosis with a shift to the left, accompanied by NRBCs?","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/WBC differentials/2"},{"choices": ["Replacement of normal marrow precursors by leukemic cells causing anemia","Decrease in functional leukocytes causing infection","Hemorrhage secondary to thrombocytopenia","Decreased erythropoietin production"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Decreased erythropoietin production","explanation": "A normal physiological response to anemia would be an increase in the kidney’s production of erythropoietin. The accumulation of leukemic cells in bone marrow leads to marrow failure, which manifests as anemia, thrombocytopenia, and granulocytopenia"},"question": "The basic pathophysiological mechanisms responsible for producing signs and symptoms in leukemia include all of the following except:","reference": "Hematology/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Leukemia/2"},{"choices": ["Acute myeloid leukemia, minimally differentiated","Acute myeloid leukemia, without maturation","Acute myelomonocytic leukemia","Acute monocytic leukemia"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Acute monocytic leukemia","explanation": "Acute monocytic leukemia has an incidence of 1% to 8% of all acute leukemias. It has a distinctive clinical manifestation of monocytic involvement, resulting in skin and gum hyperplasia. The WBC count is markedly elevated, and prognosis is poor"},"question": "Which type of acute myeloid leukemia is called the true monocytic leukemia and follows an acute or subacute course characterized by monoblasts, promonocytes, and monocytes?","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to make identifications/Leukemia/2"},{"choices": ["1–15 years","20–35 years","45–60 years","60–75 years"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "1–15 years","explanation": "ALL usually affects children from ages 1 to 15 years and is the most common type of acute leukemia in this age group. In addition, ALL constitutes the single most prevalent malignancy in pediatric patients"},"question": "In which age group does ALL occur with the highest frequency?","reference": "Hematology/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Leukemia/1"},{"choices": ["Acute myeloid leukemia, without maturation","Acute promyelocytic leukemia (PML)","Acute myelomonocytic leukemia","Acute monocytic leukemia"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Acute promyelocytic leukemia (PML)","explanation": "In patients with acute PML, the azurophilic granules in the leukemic promyelocytes contain thromboplastic substances. When released from promyelocytes, these activate soluble coagulation factors causing DIC"},"question": "Disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) is most often associated with which of the following types of acute leukemia?","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Leukemia/DIC/2"},{"choices": ["Thalassemia","Leukemia","Polycythemia vera (PV)","Myelofibrosis"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Leukemia","explanation": "A disproportionate increase in the myeloid component of bone marrow is usually the result of a leukemic state. The normal M:E ratio is approximately 4:1 in adults with normal cellularity"},"question": "An M:E ratio of 10:1 is most often seen in:","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Bone marrow/M:E/2"},{"choices": ["They are composed of azurophilic granules","They stain positive on periodic acid–Schiff (PAS) staining","They are predominantly seen in chronic myelogenous leukemia (CML)","They are nonspecific esterase positive"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "They are composed of azurophilic granules","explanation": "Auer rods are a linear projection of primary azurophilic granules and are present in the cytoplasm of myeloblasts and monoblasts in patients with acute leukemia"},"question": "Which of the following is a characteristic of Auer rods?","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Leukocytes/Auer rods/1"},{"choices": ["Pernicious anemia","Acute myeloid leukemia, without maturation","Acute erythroid leukemia","Acute myelomonocytic leukemia"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Acute erythroid leukemia","explanation": "In acute erythroid leukemia, greater than 50% of nucleated bone marrow cells are erythroid and greater than 30% nonerythroid cells are blasts. Pernicious anemia results in pancytopenia and low vitamin B12 concentrations"},"question": "SITUATION: The following laboratory values are seen: WBC = 6.0 × 109/L Hgb = 6.0 g/dL RBC = 1.90 × 1012/L Hct = 18.5% PLT = 130 × 109/L Serum vitamin B12 and folic acid: normal WBC Differential Bone Marrow 6% PMNs 40% myeloblasts 40% lymphocytes 60% promegaloblasts 4% monocytes 40 megaloblastoid NRBCs/100 WBCs 50% blasts These results are most characteristic of:","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to make identifications/Leukemia/3"},{"choices": ["Hodgkin lymphoma","Myeloproliferative disorder","Leukemoid reaction","Acute lymphocytic leukemia"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Acute lymphocytic leukemia","explanation": "Common signs of ALL are hepatosplenomegaly (65%), lymphadenopathy (50%), and fever (60%). Anemia and thrombocytopenia are usually present, and the WBC count is variable. The numerous lymphoblasts are generally PAS positive"},"question": "A 24-year-old man with Down syndrome presents with fever, pallor, lymphadenopathy, and hepatosplenomegaly. His CBC results are as follows: WBC = 10.8 × 109/L RBC = 1.56 × 1012/L 8% PMNs Hgb = 3.3 g/dL 25% lymphocytes Hct = 11% 67% PAS-positive blasts PLT = 2.5 × 109/L These findings are suggestive of:","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Leukemia/3"},{"choices": ["Acute myelocytic leukemia (AML)","CML","Acute undifferentiated leukemia (AUL)","ALL"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Acute myelocytic leukemia (AML)","explanation": "AML blasts stain positive for SBB and peroxidase. Usually, less than 10% blasts are found in peripheral blood smears from patients with CML, unless there has been a transition to blast crisis. The organelles in the cells of AUL are not mature enough to stain positive for SBB or peroxidase. Blasts in ALL are characteristically negative with these stains"},"question": "SITUATION: A peripheral blood smear shows 75% blasts. These stain positive for both Sudan Black B (SBB) and peroxidase. Given these values, which of the following disorders is most likely?","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Leukemia/Cytochemical stains/3"},{"choices": ["PAS","Myeloperoxidase","SBB","Terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase (TdT)"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "SBB","explanation": "Phospholipids, neutral fats, and sterols are stained by SBB. The PAS reaction stains intracellular glycogen. Myeloperoxidase is an enzyme present in the primary granules of myeloid cells and, to a lesser degree, in monocytic cells. TdT is a DNA polymerase found in thymus-derived lymphocytes and some bone marrow–derived lymphocytes"},"question": "In myeloid cells, the stain that selectively identifies phospholipid in the membranes of both primary and secondary granules is:","reference": "Hematology/Apply principles of special procedures/Leukemia/Cytochemical stains/3"},{"choices": ["Megakaryocytes","Monocytes","Erythrocytes","Granulocytes"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Monocytes","explanation": "NASDA stains monocytes (and monoblasts) and granulocytes (and myeloblasts). The addition of fluoride renders monocytic cells (and blasts) negative, thus allowing for differentiation from granulocytic cells, which remain positive"},"question": "Sodium fluoride may be added to the naphthyl ASD acetate (NASDA) esterase reaction. The fluoride is added to inhibit a positive reaction with:","reference": "Hematology/Apply principles of special procedures/Leukocytes/Cytochemical stains/2"},{"choices": ["B-cell ALL","T-cell ALL","Null-cell ALL","Common ALL"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Common ALL","explanation": "The majority of non-T, non-B ALL blast cells display the CALLA marker. Lymphoblasts of common ALL are TdT positive and CALLA positive but do not have surface membrane IgM or μ-chains and are pre-B lymphoblasts. Common ALL has a lower relapse rate and better prognosis compared with other immunologic subtypes of B-cell ALL"},"question": "Leukemic lymphoblasts reacting with anti–common acute lymphoblastic leukemia antigen (anti-CALLA) are characteristically seen in:","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Leukemia/Immunochemical reactions/2"},{"choices": ["TdT and PAS","Chloroacetate esterase and nonspecific esterase","SBB and peroxidase","New methylene blue and acid phosphatase"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "TdT and PAS","explanation": "PAS is positive in about 50% of ALL with L1 and L2 morphology but is negative in ALL with L3 morphology (B-cell ALL). TdT is positive in all types of ALL except L3. Both TdT and PAS are negative in AML"},"question": "Which of the following reactions are often positive in ALL but are negative in AML?","reference": "Hematology/Apply principles of special procedures/Leukemia/Special tests/2"},{"choices": ["AML","Chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL)","Acute PML","ALL"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "ALL","explanation": "SBB stains phospholipids and other neutral fats. It is the most sensitive stain for granulocytic precursors. Lymphoid cells rarely stain positive with SBB. Because 70% lymphoblasts would never be seen in CLL, the correct response is ALL"},"question": "A patient’s peripheral blood smear and bone marrow both show 70% blasts. These cells are negative on SBB staining. Given these data, which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","reference": "Hematology/Apply principles of special procedures/Leukemia/Cytochemical stains/2"},{"choices": ["CML","Chronic neutrophilic leukemia (CNL)","Chronic eosinophilic leukemia (CEL)","All of these options are classified as MPN"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "All of these options are classified as MPN","explanation": "The WHO classification system includes the following disorders under MPN: CML, CNL, CEL, essential thrombocythemia (ET), PV, primary (idiopathic) myelofibrosis, hypereosinophilic syndrome, mast cell disease, and MPNs unclassified"},"question": "Which of the following leukemias are included in the 2008 World Health Organization classification of myeloproliferative neoplasms (MPN)?","reference": "Hematology/Leukemias/Apply knowledge of special procedures/Classifications/2"},{"choices": ["Proteomics","Cytogenetic abnormalities","Carbohydrate-associated tumor antigen production","Cell signaling and adhesion markers"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Cytogenetic abnormalities","explanation": "In addition to morphology, cytochemical stains, and flow cytometry, the WHO classification relies heavily on chromosomal and molecular abnormalities"},"question": "In addition to morphology, cytochemistry, and immunophenotyping, the WHO classification of myelo- and lymphoproliferative disorders is based on which characteristic?","reference": "Hematology/Leukemias/Apply knowledge of special procedures/Classifications/1"},{"choices": ["At least 30%","At least 20%","At least 10%","Any percentage"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "At least 20%","explanation": "The WHO classification of AML requires that 20% or greater of nucleated bone marrow cells be blasts, whereas the French–American-British (FAB) classification generally requires 30% or greater. The WHO classifies AML into five subgroups: acute myeloid leukemias with recurrent genetic disorders; acute myeloid leukemia with multilineage dysplasia; acute myeloid leukemia and myelodysplastic syndromes, therapy related; acute myeloid leukemia (not otherwise categorized); and acute leukemia of ambiguous lineage"},"question": "The WHO classification requires what percentage for the blast count in blood or bone marrow for the diagnosis of AML?","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge of special procedures/Leukemias/Classifications/2"},{"choices": ["AML with t(15;17)","AML with mixed lineage","AML with t(8;21)","AML with inv(16)"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "AML with t(8;21)","explanation": "AML with t(8;21) is classified under the category “AML with Recurrent Genetic Abnormalities” by the WHO. This translocation occurs in up to 15% of cases of AML and may be the most common translocation. The AML1–ETO translocation occurs chiefly in younger patients and often in cases of acute myeloblastic leukemia with maturation, FAB M2. The translocation involves the fusion of the AML1 gene on chromosome 21 with the ETO gene on chromosome 8"},"question": "What would be the most likely designation by the WHO for AML M2 by the FAB classification?","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge of special procedures/Leukemias/Classifications/3"},{"choices": ["AML with t(15;17)","AML with mixed lineage","AML with t(8;21)","AML with inv(16)"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "AML with t(15;17)","explanation": "AML with t(15;17) is classified under the category “AML with Recurrent Genetic= Abnormalities” by the WHO. Acute PML (known as M3 under the FAB system) is composed of abnormal promyelocytes with heavy granulation, sometimes obscuring the nucleus, and abundant cytoplasm. Acute PML contains a translocation that results in the fusion of a transcription factor called PML on chromosome 15 with the alpha (α)-retinoic acid receptor gene (RARα) on chromosome 17"},"question": "What would be the most likely designation by the WHO for AML M3 by the FAB classification?","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge of special procedures/Leukemias/Classifications/3"},{"choices": ["AML with t(15;17)","AML with mixed lineage","AML with t(8;21)","AML with inv(16)"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "AML with inv(16)","explanation": "AML with inv(16) has pericentric inversion of chromosome 16 and is associated with M4 with marrow eosinophilia, M4eo under the FAB system. The inv(16) results in the fusion of the CBFβ gene on 16q22 with the MYH11 gene on 16p13"},"question": "Which AML cytogenetic abnormality is associated with AML M4 with marrow eosinophilia under the WHO classification of AML with recurrent genetic abnormalities?","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge of special procedures/Leukemias/Classifications/3"},{"choices": ["Acute myeloid leukemias with recurrent genetic abnormalities","Acute myeloid leukemia with multilineage dysplasia","Acute megakaryoblastic leukemia classified under AML (not otherwise categorized)","Acute leukemias of ambiguous lineage"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Acute megakaryoblastic leukemia classified under AML (not otherwise categorized)","explanation": "Acute megakaryoblastic leukemia, which is equivalent to FAB M7, is a relatively uncommon form of leukemia characterized by neoplastic proliferation of megakaryoblasts and atypical megakaryocytes. Recognition of this entity was aided by the use of platelet peroxidase (PPO) ultrastructural studies. PPO is distinct from myeloperoxidase and is specific for the megakaryocytic cell line. Acute megakaryoblastic leukemia is defined as an acute leukemia in which 50% or greater of the blasts are of megakaryocytic lineage. In the WHO 2016 revision, it is classified under “AML (not otherwise categorized)."},"question": "What would be the most likely classification by the WHO for AML M7 by the FAB classification?","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge of special procedures/Leukemias/Classifications/3"}],"type": "MULTIPLE_CHOICE"}],"topic": "Acute Leukemias"}],"edition": "5th","title": "Medical Laboratory Science Review"}